A Guide to the Rockefeller University records, Corporation, Board of Trustees, Committees FA860
Rockefeller Archive Center
Rockefeller University records, Corporation, Board of Trustees, Committees
1909-1984
Rockefeller Archive Center
Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research
Gates, Frederick Taylor
Rockefeller University
FA860
6 Box(es)
6 boxes.
Biographical / Historical
CORPORATION
In May 1908 the Charter of The Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research was amended to permit the creation of a not more than nine member Board of Trustees to have exclusive control of the real property and the principal of all permanent funds of the Corporation. By-Laws for the Corporation were established October 1910. The members of the first Board of Trustees were: William H. Welch, Frederick T. Gates, Simon Flexner, Starr J. Murphy and John D. Rockefeller, Jr. The first meeting of the Board of Trustees was held October 17, 1910.
Elected officers were President, Vice-President, Secretary and Treasurer of the Corporation. The first three names were required to be members of the Board of Trustees. The Trustees were empowered to appoint, on the nomination of the Board of Scientific Directors, a General Manager to represent the Board of Trustees in the care and maintenance of the real property of the Corporation. Functioning of the Board of Trustees was through an Executive Committee (of not more than six, including the President) and a Finance Committee (composed of three members elected from the Board by the Board) which was deemed to be in continuous session. Two members were elected for the Budget Committee, a joint committee with the Board of Scientific Directors to approve the annual budget for the scientific work of the Institute, within the limits of the yearly balance of available income. The Board was empowered to appoint such assistants to the Treasurer or other agents and employees as were necessary.
The original By-Laws of the Corporation provided a relatively complicated formula for determining the composition of the members elected to the Board of Trustees, but amendment to the By-Laws in 1928 simplified the Rules to provide for two Trustees appointed by the Scientific Directors, one Trustee named by John D. Rockefeller or John D. Rockefeller, Jr., and the remaining members on a majority vote of the members of the Corporation at an annual meeting or special meeting called for that purpose. May 28, 1914 additional clarifications were made in the Trustees' Rules to further define the authority and powers of the Finance Committee.
Resolutions were taken from time to time, governing the use of income. In 1915 it was resolved that any surplus income accumulated in any one year be added to permanent endowment to be used for non-recurring expenses. However, by 1939, in an effort to secure a downward trend in the size of the budget and to adjust to changes in the economy the 1915 resolution was rescinded.
The first addition to the Board of Trustees was in 1913 when Jerome D. Greene was elected, to the Board. He served until 1932. Starr J. Murphy died in 1921 and was replaced by Raymond B. Fosdick (1921-1936). The next added was Trevor Arnett (1926-1937). Further additions to the Board of Trustees were: Charles W. Appleton (1928-1940), George Murnane (1928- ), Henry James (1929-1947), John D. Rockefeller, 3rd (1932-1950), David Rockefeller (1940-), who wan on leave with the Armed Forces 1942-45, John C. Traphagen (1936-1959), Frederick Osborn, (1938-1946), Barklie Henry (1947-1966), Lindsley F. Kimball (1947-1971), Donald K. David (1950-1971). From the Board of Scientific Directors, Herbert S. Gasser succeeded Simon Flexner in 1935; Charles R. Stockard succeeded William H. Welch in 1936, and George H. Whipple succeeded Charles Stockard in 1939.
The first officers of the Board of Trustees were: Frederick T. Gates, President; William H. Welch, Vice-President; and Starr J. Murphy, Secretary. Upon the death of F.T. Gates in 1929, John D. Rockefeller, Jr. was elected President of the Board of Trustees and was reelected until he requested that his name not be placed in nominational the expiration of his term October 1950. (He resigned as a Trustee in 1954). John D. Rockefeller, Jr. was succeeded as President in 1950 by David Rockefeller. William H. Welch was succeeded as Vice-President in 1933 by Simon Flexner who retired in 1935. No action was taken on the vice-presidency until 1937 when Henry James was elected and served until 1947. George Hoyt Whipple was elected Vice-President in 1947. Starr J. Murphy resigned as secretary in 1921 and was succeeded by Raymond Blaine Fosdick who resigned in 1936. Trevor Arnett was elected Secretary in 1936 and resigned within a year. In 1937 Edric B. Smith (who was also Business Manager of the Institute) became Secretary and served until 1954.
Starr J. Murphy served also as Counsel to the Board of Trustees until his death in 1921; Aubin L. Boulware was Counsel 1921-June 1923. A more formal arrangement started September 1924 with Thomas McElrath Debevoise who served until 1958; Associate Counsel 1934-1947 was Chauncey Belknap and from 1947 John Edwards Lockwood. Mr. Lockwood became Counsel in 1959 and served until 1968/69. Donal Clare O'Brien, Associate Counsel from 1955/56 became Counsel in 1969/70.
In 1953 an extensive reorganization began. New By-Laws adopted June 23, 1953 provided that "The members of the Corporation shall consist of the members of the Board of Trustees and the members of the Board of Scientific Directors as those Boards are constituted on the 23rd day of June 1953 and hereafter the said Boards shall be merged into one Board known as the Board of Trustees".
The new By-Laws for the Corporation were adopted to implement the recommendations made in the Report of the Committee on Nomination and Review which had been appointed October 26, 1951 to "review the fundamental policies of the Institute." The Chairman of the Board was designated the chief policy officer of the Corporation to interpret the policies determined by the Board of Trustees, and the President the chief executive officer of the Corporation to have general supervision over the business of the Corporation and over the several staff officers subject to the control of the Board of Trustees and responsible for the work of the Institute.
The business of the Board of Trustees was implemented by three elected committees: and Executive Committee of between 5 and 7 members including the Chairman; a Finance Committee of between 3 and 5 members (as amended January 1957) to handle investments and advise on financial policy and a policy; and a Budget Committee of between 3 and 5 members to review the budget proposed by the President each year and recommend on its adoption by the Board of Trustees. At the moment of reorganization much of the administrative procedure was determined by Resolution to continue in previous patterns while business and financial studies were in progress.
The first officers elected were: David Rockefeller, Chairman of the Board; George Hoyt Whipple, Vice-Chairman; Detlev Bronk, President; Thomas M. Rivers, Vice-President. Executive officers were Edward Robinson as Treasurer and Edric Brooks Smith who continued as Business Manager and Secretary until his retirement October 1955. Other members of the new Board of Trustees were: Lindsley Fiske Kimball, Donald Kirk David, Ross Granville Harrison, John C. Traphagen, Alphonse Raymond Dochez, Vincent du Vigneaud, Barklie Henry, George Murnane and John Davison Rockefeller, Jr.
As the changing character of the Institute evolved, By-Laws were amended, Resolutions were rescinded and changes were instituted to provide for the development of the Institute along the lines suggested by the Report of the Committee on Nomination and Review. To the three committees originally provided in the By-Laws was added an elected Committee on Audit. Added also were appointive committees: Committee on Educational Policies, Committee on Research, Committee on Business Operations, Committee on Buildings and Grounds and a Committee on Nominations. January 30, 1957 a Committee on Hospital Affairs was appointed to review present and future hospital policies.
In 1955, Thomas M. Rivers, Vice-President and Director of the Institute retired and at that time resolutions were taken to discontinue the division of the Institute into Departments, to eliminate the position of Director of the Institute and to provide for several Vice-Presidents, Frank L. Horsfall served as Vice-President for Clinical Studies 1955-1957 and Douglas Whitaker was Vice-President for Administration 1955-1964. When Edric Smith retired in 1955, John E. Lockwood then Assistant Counsel became, in addition, Secretary of the Board and after the death in 1958 of Thomas Debevoise he became in 1959 both Secretary and Counsel.
New members of the Board of Trustees were: in 1954, Robert Loeb, Eli Whitney Debevoise, Kenneth C. Brownell (1954-1958); in 1956, William J. Robbins; in 1957, Philip Bard; in 1958, Albert L. Nickerson; in 1960, J. Richardson Dilworth and William O. Baker; in 1961 Baron Edgar Douglas Adrian; in 1966 George F. Bennett and Frederick Seitz; in 1968, Philip Handler and John W. Gardner; in 1969, Thomas Grady Cousins, Walter N. Rothschild, Jr., Robert Gregg Stone and Chauncey William Wallace Cook; in 1970, Christian Archibald Herter, Jr. Resignations from the Board of Trustees were: in 1954, John D. Rockefeller, Jr.; 1955, Thomas M. Rivers; 1957 Ross Granville Harrison; 1959 John C. Traphagen and Alphonse Raymond Dochez; 1964 George Murnane; 1965 Baron Edgar Douglas Adrian; 1966 William J. Robbins and Barklie McKee Henry died in 1966.
George H. Whipple who had served on the Board of Scientific Directors and been their elected representative on the Board of Trustees and its Vice-President became a member of the newly constituted Board of Trustees in 1953. He was elected Vice-Chairman and held that office until his resignation in October 1960. Robert F. Loeb was then elected Vice-Chairman of the Board where he served until he resigned May 1970 and was succeeded by William O. Baker.
Changes in Charter and By-Laws were made as the changes in Institute organization developed. In May 1965 the Corporate name was changed to The Rockefeller University and the new Charter and amended By-Laws were published in 1966. They provided that the number of Trustees be between five and twenty-five; that elected officers be a Chairman, Vice-Chairman, and a President all of whom shall be or become Trustees. Other elected officers were to be Secretary and Treasurer, one or more Vice-Presidents, Assistant Secretaries and Assistant Treasurers and other officers as considered necessary by the Board. One person may be elected to more than one office except that President and Secretary may not be the same person. Officers are elected for one year or until respective successors are elected.
On the retirement of Detlev Bronk (who became a Trustee Emeritus) in October 1968, Frederick Seitz was elected President; C. Eugene Sunderlin was elected to succeed John E. Lockwood as Secretary at the time of Mr. Lockwood's retirement and Donal C. O'Brien, Jr. became Counsel at that time.
Board changes:
Additions: Bearn, Alexander G. 1970; Hildebrand, John G. 1970; Kac, Mark 1970; Yang, Chen Ning 1970; Bassine, Charles C. 1971; Casimir, Hendrik E.G. 1971; Haggerty, Patrick E. 1971; Heiskell, Marion S. 1971; Rockefeller, David, Jr. 1971; Whitehead, Edwin C. 1971; Linen, James A. III 1972; Astor, Brooke (Mrs. Vincent Astor) 1972
Retirements or Resignations: David, Donald K. 1971; Gardner, John W. 1971; Kimball, Lindsley 1971; Cook, Chauncey William W. 1972
Resignation: Kac, Mark 1973; Hildebrand, John G. 1973
Additions: Griffin, Donald R. 1973; Williams, Robley C. Jr. 1973
Additions: Ralph E. Ablon 1974; Nicholas F. Brady 1974
In October of 1975 David Rockefeller resigned as Chairman of the Board of Trustees and became Chairman of the Trustees' Executive Committee in order to concentrate his attention on the University's program to broaden its base of private support. He was succeeded as Chairman of the Board by Patrick E. Haggerty.
New Board appointments: Dr. Lewis Thomas 1975; Dr. Seymour S. Kety 1976; Mrs. Anne E. Reed 1976; Dr. P. Roy Vagelos 1976; Richard M. Furlaud 1976; John R. Stevenson 1976; Neva Rockefeller Kaiser 1977; Norman F. Ramsey 1977; Alexander D. Forger 1978; J. Paul Sticht 1978; Frank T. Cary 1978; Pamela Harriman 1979; David A. Hamburg 1979; Curtis L. Blake 1980
Retirements: resignations: Philip Bard 1974-1975; David Rockefeller, Jr. 1977; Patrick E Haggerty died suddenly October 1, 1980; William O. Baker elected Chairman of Bd. of Trustees October 21, 1980
Biographical/Historical note
CORPORATION
The Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research was founded in 1901, in New York City, by John D. Rockefeller for the purpose of medical research with special reference to the prevention and treatment of disease. Control rested in seven Directors of the Corporation. Funds from the original grant, provided up to an average of $ 20,000 a year for ten years. In June 1902, a second pledge of $ 1,000,000 over ten years was made. These funds were informally handled by drawing upon Mr. Rockefeller's office against the amounts which had been pledged. In November 1907, when Mr. Rockefeller announced an endowment fund to the Institute of $ 2,600,000 in stocks and bonds, the transfer could not be made directly to the Directors since the Charter of 1901 did not give the Corporation specific authority to hold invested funds. The funds earmarked for the Institute were thus included in a gift to the General Education Board.
In May 1908 the Charter was amended to permit the Corporation to create, either by contract or by-law with the donor, a Board of Trustees empowered to hold investments. October 15, 1910 By-Laws for a Board of Trustees were adopted and a further gift of $3,820,000 was announced, thus providing an endowment of $ 6,420,000. Additional gifts from John D. Rockefeller gave the Trustees of the Institute more than $34,000,000 in land, buildings and endowment over the first twenty years. In 1928 Mr. Rockefeller made another gift of $ 20,000,000. By 1953 the dollar value of the Institute's endowment was $ 107,000,000.
The Board of Directors was supplanted, in the Charter amendment of 1908, by a Board of Trustees and a Board of Scientific Directors, (the original Board of Directors) as members of the Corporation. As provided in the 1910 By-Laws, the real property and the principal of all permanent funds were under the exclusive control of the Board of Trustees; all of the scientific work of the Institute, including the work of the Hospital was to be under the exclusive control of the Board of Scientific Directors.
The Corporation functioned through a five-man Budget Committee comprised of three members chosen by the Board of Scientific Directors and two members chosen by the Board of Trustees. Further changes in By-Laws in 1928 provided that of the three Budget Committee members representing the Scientific Directors, at least one, was to be also a member of the Board of Trustees. In 1937 further changes in By-Laws provided that any portion of the income for any year not expended in accordance with the budget for that year, was to be under the exclusive control of the Board of Trustees.
The Board of Trustees elected the President, Vice-President, Secretary and Treasurer of the Corporation, of whom the first three officers were also the officers of the Board of Trustees. The first President was Frederick T. Gates, succeeded 1929-1950 by John D. Rockefeller, Jr., and succeeded in 1950 by David Rockefeller.
In 1953 an extensive reorganization began. New By-Laws, adopted June 23, 1953 provided [?]. The Members of the Corporation shall consist of the members of the Board of Trustees and the members of the Board of Scientific Directors as those Boards are constituted on the twenty-third day of June 1953, and hereafter the said Boards shall be merged into one Board Known as the Board of Trustees.
The Board of Trustees was also designated the Corporate Board of Directors. Elected officers were Chairman of the Board, Vice-chairman, President, Vice-President, Secretary and Treasurer. David Rockefeller was named the first Chairman of the Board and Detlev W. Bronk was named the first President of the Institute.
November 19, 1954 the Charter of the Institute was amended by the Board of Regents, for and on behalf of the Education Department of the State of New York, so as to authorize the Institute to grant degrees. The Corporation thus became part of the University of the State of New York, subject to the jurisdiction and visitation of the Regents of the said University in all respects as though the Corporation had been originally incorporated by the Regents. June 1958 the Charter of the Institute was again amended to change the name from The Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research to The Rockefeller Institute.
On May 27, 1965 the Board of Regents amended the Charter of the Institute in its entirety and changed the corporate name from The Rockefeller Institute to The Rockefeller University.
In accordance with By-Laws adopted October 17, 1966 the Corporation shall consist of the members of the Board of Trustees as constituted from time to time.
CORPORARTION Board of Directors (1901-1910)
Under certificate of incorporation dated May 28, 1901 and filed in the office of the Secretary of State and of the Clerk of New York County on June 13, 1901, control of the Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research rested in a seven-man Board of Directors. May 6, 1908 the Charter was amended to allow creation of a Board of Trustees by by-law or contract. By-Laws for this change were not adopted until October 15, 1910.
At the first meeting, June 14, 1901 the officers elected were: William H. Welch, President; T. Mitchell Prudden, Vice-President; L. Emmett Holt, Secretary, and Christian A. Herter, Treasurer. Three other Directors were Theobald Smith, Hermann M. Biggs and Simon Flexner who at a meeting on October 25, 1902 was unanimously elected Director of the Institute.
Planning, business and work of the Institute were carried on under the direction of the seven Directors, operating through an Executive Committee, composed of three members and the President, and amended April 21, 1906 to four elected members and the Director of the Laboratories, ex-officio. Special committees, such as a Committee on Library and Supplies, a Building Committee and a Committee on Equipment were appointed for short periods and special ongoing needs. April 10, 1909 a Finance Committee, of three members from the Executive Committee was established. Administrative functions were carried by the Directors until January 1906 when James U. Norris, Superintendent; N. Curtice Holt, Clerk (to keep books and accounts of the Institute) and a library stenographer were employed.
When the main laboratory with animal house and power house were ready for use a formal dedication was held on May 11, 1906 with addresses by L. Emmett Holt, William H. Welch, President Nicholas Murray Butler of Columbia University and Charles W. Eliot of Harvard.
By July 1910, a General Manager, Jerome D. Greene was added to the administrative staff.
Board of Scientific Directors (1910-1953):
As provided by the By-Laws of 1910 control of all scientific work of the Institute, including the work of the Hospital was under the exclusive control of the not-more than seven-man Board of Scientific Directors. The Charter change in 1910 provided that successors of the first Board of Directors be elected by the Board of Trustees from candidates nominated by the Scientific Directors.
Executive organization consisted of an Executive Committee, Budget Committee and a Committee on the Hospital, which last was dropped in the amended Rules January 19, 1918. Committee members were elected at the Annual Meeting, but amended in 1946 to provide that the term be for one year and until the election of successors. Administrative officers were the Director (clearly provided after 1924), Director of the Laboratories, Director of the Hospital, between 1915-1930 a Director of the Department of Animal Pathology, and between 1930-1951 a Director of the Department of Animal and Plant Pathology. Another administrative officer was a General Manager, to be Treasurer of the Board of Scientific Directors (amended October 14, 1911... shall act as treasurer...). The General Manager (amended January 11, 1913 to Manager; amended April 20, 1918 to Business Manager) was authorized to draw upon the Treasurer of the Board of Trustees for the sums of money needed to meet Institute expenses authorized under the budget. Administrative officers were originally elected by the Board of Scientific Directors to serve at its pleasure. Later amendments provided that the Director be an appointment of the Corporation on nomination of a committee composed of three from the Scientific Directors and three from the Board of Trustees. The Business Manager, selected by the Scientific Directors was appointed by the Board of Trustees. Other administrative officers were elected by the Board itself. Appointive positions, at the discretion of the Board of Scientific Directors, were Deputy Business Manager, Assistant Business Manager, Bursar and a group of hospital positions.
Changes in the By-Laws of the Corporation in 1928 provided that the not-more than seven-man Board of Scientific Directors have no more than two who were actively engaged in scientific work for the Corporation. This was further modified in 1934 so that the Board of Scientific Directors was to consist of the Director and no more than six others with only the Director of the Institute being an. active member of the staff engaged in scientific work for the Corporation. Also provided was that the appointment of the Director of the Institute was to constitute his election as a member of the Board of Scientific Directors to hold office until the end of his service as Director of the Institute. October 28, 1933 the By-Laws of the Corporation were amended to provide that a member of the Board of Scientific Directors, on retirement from the Board, could, on recommendation or with the approval of the Board of Scientific Directors be given, by the Board of Trustees, the honorary title of Member Emeritus of the Board of Scientific Directors. At the same time, the By-Laws regarding a vacancy on the Board of Scientific Directors provided that for each vacancy at least two candidates be nominated by the Scientific Directors for election by the Board of Trustees.